{
  "reference_number": "12263",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "While long-lived gases have greater long-term effects, human civilisation has to survive in the short term."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Businesses and the NZ public need certainty and transparency. Domestic emission reductions are easier to see and enable greater\n trust that everyone is doing their bit."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There should be no extensions of the target but if circumstances indicate that reductions need to be made faster, the target could\n be shortened."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "In my view the advantage of the 5-yearly periods is that they straddle the political 3-yearly cycle and encourage bipartisan\n government."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "The government should have plans and timeframes which make changes that are consistent and understandable with an overall\n\n framework."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes if technological advances allow for more effective emission controls and the government wants to speed up the adoption of\n\nimproved technologies or management systems."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Apart from the considerations set out on page 44, the Commission needs to consider the impact of a decision on SOCIAL EQUITY\nand IMPACTS, INCLUDING POSSIBLE BENEFITS, TO THE ENVIRONMENT AND INDIGENOUS BIODIVERSITY."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The plans need to be made public and should provide guidance for local and regional governments under the Resource\nManagement Act or replacement legislation."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government needs to work with private sector players such as farmers and the transport industry but also with local and regional\n\ngovernment."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I would like to see the Commission as one that has a strong Advisory role, with mechanisms built in to hold Government to account"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Don't know"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I agree with the areas of expertise indicated on p. 45 but IN ADDITION, THE COMMISSION NEEDS EXPERTISE IN SOCIAL IMPACT\nASSESSMENT."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "YES. Adapting to climate change is the critically relevant parallel to reducing emissions. For example, reduction of greenhouse gas\n\nemissions from agriculture will require major changes in agricultural practice at the same time that agriculture also has to adapt to\nchanging weather and climate."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "In addition to the elements indicated on page 46, I think the government will need i) A PRO-ACTIVE EDUCATIONAL AND ADIVISORY\n\nROLE - which could be a purpose designed element of the Climate Change Commission or sit somewhere in the Ministry for the\nEnvironment; and (ii) I think it will need an AGENCY TO CO-ORDINATE DISASTER RESPONSES. There are going to be more events\n\nwhere communities are completely overwhelmed by flood or drought or other weather related disasters and need assistance to get\nback on their feet."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I consider that emissions reductions in GHGs as well as adaptations to climate change will involve major changes to land use and\n\nurban development. For that reason, I suggest the following changes to Part 4 of the Resource Management Act, Functions, powers,\nand duties of central and local government: o Minister for the Environment: add the duty to prepare and update a national adaptation\nplan, the plan to set targets for emission reductions of CO2, Nitrous Oxide and methane; the plan to be reviewed and up-dated at\n\nintervals of not more than a 5-years; o The Minister for the Environment to monitor and publish the results of emission reduction\nactions and targets every 2 years. o Regional councils: add the duty to prepare regional adaptation plans in close cooperation with\n\ndistrict councils, iwi and central government ministries (for biosecurity, primary production and health) o Regional councils: to include\nCO2 targets and nutrient limits in regional plans; o Regional councils: insert a requirement of regional transport plans an aim to\n\nreduce transport modes based on fossil fuels and optimise other modes of access than the private car. o District councils: require\ndistrict councils to incorporate subdivision regulations that maximise access by walking and/or cycling. o District Councils: encourage\ndistrict councils to maintain and up-date codes of practice for subdivision, residential design and land development that specify best\n\npractice."
    }
  ]
}
